Register of the A. (Andrei) Siniavskii Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
A. (Andrei) Siniavskii papers,
1916-1998
98054
Siniavskii, A. (Andrei), 1925-1997
130 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (55.1 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Writings, diaries, correspondence, interrogation and trial records, printed matter, sound recordings, photographs, and memorabilia, relating to Russian literature, civil rights in the Soviet Union, political trials and conditions of political prisoners in the Soviet Union, and Russian émigré affairs. Includes records of the Russian-language Paris journal Sintaksis, published and edited by A. Siniavskii.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1998.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1925 Born, Moscow, U.S.S.R.
1941-1945 Graduates from the Moscow Aviation School and serves as an airfield radio technician
1946-1952 Studies at Moscow University Receives doctorate in literature
1952-1965 Teaches literature at the Gorkii Institute of World Literature, Moscow University, and the Moscow Art Theater Co-author of books on Russian poetry, author of articles in Novyi mir, and of an introduction to Boris Pasternak: Stikhotvoreniia i poemy Author of essay On Socialist Realism and creative writings, published abroad under the pseudonym of Abram Terts
1965 Arrested for dissemination of anti-Soviet propaganda. Imprisoned in Lubianka and Lefortovo prisons. Sentenced to seven years of hard labor
1966-1971 Serves part of sentence in Potma (Mordovia) labor camps Is released early and returns to Moscow
1973 Emigrates to Paris, France
1973-1975 Author, under the pseudonym of Abram Terts, of Golos iz khora, Progulki s Pushkinym, and V teni Gogolia
1978 With Mariia Rozanova, begins publication of the journal Sintaksis
1980 Author, under the pseudonym of Abram Terts, of Kroshka Tsores
1982 Author, "Opavshie list'ia" V. V. Rozanova
1984 Author, under the pseudonym of Abram Terts, of Spokoinoi nochi
1988 Author, Sovetskaia tsivilizatsiia
1991 Author, Ivan-durak: Ocherk russkoi narodnoi very
1996 Dies, Paris, France
Scope and Content Note
The Andrei Siniavskii papers consist of material related to the life and work of the Russian writer and political activist Andrei Siniavskii, both in Russia and abroad, from the 1930's to 1997.
The collection includes a wealth of biographical material related to his family and childhood, found in the series related to his parents, Donat Siniavskii and Evdokiia-Torkhova-Siniavskaia. Of special interest, here, are the diaries of his mother, which include descriptions of his childhood and childhood drawings. The biographical file further includes documentary material related to the trial of Andrei Siniavskii and Iulii Daniel, as well as reports in the Western press about his arrest, trial and exile to France.
A major part of the collection consists of Siniavskii's scholarly work and creative writing, found in the speeches and writings series, including preparatory material, drafts and printed copies of writings on scholarly, political and cultural subjects, as well as creative writing under the pseudonym of Abram Terts. Also of interest is material related to his political activity, especially as seen through the eyes of the Western media, including newspaper interviews and radio programs.
Finally, the collection as a whole reflects the political and cultural life of the post-Soviet emigration (1970's-1980's). Of special interest in this respect is the Sintaksis file, which reflects the development of one particular trend within the former dissident movement.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Political crimes and offenses--Soviet Union.; Political prisoners--Soviet Union.; Russians in foreign countries.; Dissenters--Soviet Union.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); Russian literature.; Civil rights--Soviet Union.
Other Index Terms Related to this Collection
Sintaksis.
Series Description
- Biographical File, 1965-1992. (Box 1-6)
  Appeal for permission to emigrate; articles about Andrei Siniavskii in the foreign periodical press; autobiographical note; honors awarded to him after emigration; invitations; letters; obituaries; and material related to the trial of Andrei Siniavskii and Iulii Daniel, consisting of copies of official records of the investigation and trial. Arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1959-1998. (Box 6-12)
  Personal correspondence of Andrei Siniavskii. Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- University Lectures, n.d. (Box 12-34)
  Preparatory material and texts of lectures delivered at the Sorbonne, Paris. Arranged alphabetically by subject
- Speeches and Writings, 1940's-1998. (Box 34-58)
  Creative writing produced under the pseudonym of Abram Terts, including holograph drafts, printed translations and reviews; dissertation reviews; interviews published in the periodical press; juvenilia, including childhood art work and writing; literary criticism and scholarly articles re Andrei Siniavskii and his work; prison writings, including letters to his wife, Mariia Rozanova; public lectures and participation at public literary events and conferences, including printed matter and posters; radio program transcripts of readings for the BBC and Radio Liberty; scholarly work related to culture and politics, including articles, lectures, and speeches. Arranged alphabetically by type of work
- Donat Siniavskii File, 1914-1960. (Box 59-61)
  Biographical material related to Andrei Siniavskii's father, including personal documents and material related to his arrest; correspondence with Andrei Siniavskii and other family members; printed matter related to his work in village education and theater; writings, consisting of holographs, typescripts, and printed copies of newspaper articles, plays, poetry, and prose. Arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Evdokiia Torkhova-Siniavskaia File, 1855-1955. (Box 61-62)
  Biographical material related to Andrei Siniavskii's mother, including personal and family documents; correspondence, including with Andrei Siniavskii; diaries describing Andrei Siniavskii's life as a child, including childhood drawings and writings of Andrei Siniavskii. Arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Mariia Rozanova File, 1966-1999. (Box 62)
  Correspondence, interview, memorabilia, and writings, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Sintaksis File, 1968-1995. (Box 63-100)
  Material related to the journal Sintaksis, published and edited by Andrei Siniavskii and his wife, Mariia Rozanova. Includes correspondence with authors and manuscripts submitted for publication. Arranged alphabetically by physical form and therein by name of author
- Subject File, 1907-1999. (Box 100-115)
  Correspondence, writings, and printed matter, arranged alphabetically by subject or author
- Printed Matter, 1916-1997. (Box 115-119)
  Books and journals, leaflets and ephemera, and newspaper issues and clippings, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Pnotographs, 1890's-1993. (Box 120-121)
  Prints depicting Andrei Siniavskii, his family, and associates; photographs of his trips to the Russian north; photographs related to his life in emigration, including honors received. Includes prints sent to Siniavskii or Sintaksis along with articles submitted for publication. Arranged alphabetically by subject or name of collector
- Audio-Visual File, 1970's-1993. (Box 122-130)
  Phonotape recordings of lectures, speeches, round-table discussions, interviews and radio broadcasts, mostly related to the political and cultural activities of the third emigration; and videotapes of a television interview with Mariia Rozanova and of the celebration of the tenth anniversary of Andrei Siniavskii's emigration. Arranged alphabetically by physical form and therein by name of speaker
- Oversize File, 1900-1989. (Box 131 and map case)
  Award, diplomas, lithographs, maps, photographs, and posters, arranged alphabetically by physical form
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1965-1992 (Box 1)
  - Appeal of Andrei Siniavskii to the Soviet government for permisson to emigrate, 1973. (Folder 1: 1)
    Includes invitations related to the campaign in the West to obtain permission to emigrate, 1969-1973
  - Articles about Andrei Siniavskii in the periodical press
    - General
      - Belgium, 1966-1967 (Folder 1: 2)
      - Denmark, 1975 (Folder 1: 3)
      - France.
        Includes émigré press
        - 1963-1973 (Folder 1: 4)
        - 1974-1976 (Folder 1: 5)
        - 1979-1989 (Folder 1: 6)
      - Germany
        - 1969-1973 (Folder 1: 7)
        - 1974-1975 (Folder 1: 8)
        - 1976-1986 (Folder 1: 9)
      - Great Britain and United States (Box 2)
        - 1963-1976 (Folder 2: 1)
        - 1979-1991 (Folder 2: 2)
        - 1989-1992 (Folder 2: 3)
      - Iceland, 1975 (Folder 2: 4)
      - Israel, 1974 (Folder 2: 5)
      - Italy
        - Undated (Folder 2: 6)
        - 1965-1976 (Folder 2: 7)
        - 1977-1979 (Folder 2: 8)
        - 1980-1989 (Folder 2: 9)
        - 1991-1995 (Folder 2: 10)
      - Netherlands, 1980 (Box-folder 3: 1)
      - Norway, 1975-1982 (Folder 3: 2)
      - Spain (Catalan), 1985 (Folder 3: 3)
      - Sweden, 1975-1985 (Folder 3: 4)
      - Switzerland, 1974-1985 (Folder 3: 5)
    - Aucouturier, Michel. (Folder 3: 6-9)
      Collection of clippings, mostly re arrest and trial of Siniavskii and Daniel, 1960-1967
    - Editions Albin Michel, L'affaire Siniavski-Daniel. (Folder 3: 10)
      Collection of clippings, 1966-1981
    - Kastler, Claude. (Folder 3: 11)
      Notebook of clippings re arrest and trial of Siniavskii and Daniel, 1966
    - Labedz, Leopold, "The Trial in Moscow," Encounter, 1966 (Folder 3: 12)
    - Nivat, Georges, "Portrait d'André Siniavskii," n.d., See also SINTAKSIS FILE/Manuscripts submitted for publication/ Nivat, Georges (Folder 3: 13)
      Typescript. Includes biographical material and clippings.
  - Autobiographical note, n.d. (Folder 4: 1)
    Holograph
  - Honors awarded to Andrei Siniavskii
    - Bayerische Akademie der Schönen Künste, Internationaler Exil-Preis, 1988-1989. (Folder 4: 2)
      Newspaper clippings
    - Harvard University
      - Honorary degree (Doctor of Letters), 1991., See OVERSIZE FILE/Honors
      - Programs, invitation, and schedules related to the Harvard Commencement, 1991., See also PHOTOGRAPHS/Siniavskii, Andrei (Folder 4: 3)
    - International Sakharov Hearings, Freedom Prize, 1977-1979., See also CORRESPONDENCE/ International Sakharov Committee and International Sakharov Hearings; SUBJECT FILE; and OVERSIZE FILE/Honors (Folder 4: 4)
    - Rossiiskii Gosudarstvennyi Gumanitarnyi Universitet, honorary degree. Diploma, 1992
  - Invitations (Folder 4: 5)
    - Luncheon from the President of the United States, Ronald Reagan, 1982 (Folder 4: 6)
    - Receptions from the Mayor of Paris, Jacques Chirac, 1980 and the President of France, François Mitterrand, 1985 (Folder 4: 7)
  - Letters
    - Condolence, 1997. (Folder 4: 8)
      Also includes letter to the editor by Larisa Bogoraz et al.
    - Protest against the arrest and trial of Siniavskii and Daniel, collected by Michel Aucouturier, 1965-1967. (Folder 4: 9)
      Typescript and printed copies
  - Obituaries, 1997 (Folder 4: 10)
  - Trial material.
    Documents relating to the trial of Andrei Siniavskii and Iulii Daniel
    - List of material included in the case file deposited in the Tsentral'nyi Arkhiv FSB RF, n.d. (Folder 4: 11)
      Typescript
    - Criminal investigation (ugolovnoe delo) file of the KGB (Sledstvennyi Otdel), 1965-1966., See also PHOTOGRAPHS/ Siniavskii, Andrei (Folder 4: 12-14)
      Photocopy of typescript from the Tsentral'nyi Arkhiv FSB RF.
    - Criminal investigation (ugolovnoe delo) file of the KGB (Sledstvennyi Otdel), 1965-1966., See also PHOTOGRAPHS/Siniavskii, Andrei (Box-folder 5: 1-6)
    - Dossier of supervisory procedure of the procurator's office (nadzornoe proizvodstvo), 1965. (Folder 5: 7-9)
      Photocopy of material from the Gosudarstvennyi Arkhiv Rossiiskoi Federatsii (GARF). Typescript and handwritten material
    - File ("Krasnaia papka") submitted by the KGB to the Central Committee of the Communist Party, 1963-1968 (Folder 5: 10-11)
    - Trial records (sudebnoe delo), 1965. (Box-folder 6: 1-2)
      Photocopy of typescript and handwritten material from the Tsentral'nyi Arkhiv FSB RF
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1959-1998., See also SPEECHES AND WRITINGS/Prison writings/Correspondence; DONAT SINIAVSKII FILE/Correspondence; EVDOKIIA-TORKHOVA SINIAVSKAIA FILE/Correspondence; and SINTAKSIS FILE/Correspondence
  - General
    - General
      - Undated (Folder 6: 3-4)
      - 1970-1973 (Folder 6: 5)
      - 1974 (Folder 6: 6)
      - 1975 (Folder 6: 7)
      - 1976-1977 (Folder 6: 8)
      - 1978-1979 (Folder 6: 9)
      - 1980 (Folder 6: 10)
      - 1981-1983 (Folder 6: 11)
      - 1984-1985 (Box-folder 7: 1)
      - 1986-1987 (Folder 7: 2)
      - 1988-1989 (Folder 7: 3)
      - 1990 (Folder 7: 4)
      - 1991 (Folder 7: 5)
      - 1992-1993 (Folder 7: 6)
      - 1994-1996 (Folder 7: 7)
    - Drafts of letters from Andrei Siniavskii to others
      - General
        - Undated (Folder 7: 8)
        - 1974-1978 (Folder 7: 9)
        - 1985-1996 (Folder 7: 10)
      - Evtushenko, Evgenii, n.d. (Folder 7: 11)
      - Pipes, Richard, n.d. (Folder 7: 12)
      - Solzhenitsyn, Aleksandr, 1975 (Folder 7: 13)
  - A. Neimanis Buchvertrieb (Serafim Miloradovich), 1985 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Agurskii, Mikhail, 1986 (Folder 8: 2)
  - Aid to Russian Christians (Jane Ellis), 1974 (Folder 8: 3)
  - Aleshkovskii, Iuz, n.d., See also AUDIO-VISUAL FILE/Phonotapes (Folder 8: 4)
  - American University, 1978 (Folder 8: 5)
  - Amherst College, 1979-1985 (Folder 8: 6)
  - Amnesty International, 1980-1983 (Folder 8: 7)
  - Anikanov, Leonid, 1959 (Folder 8: 8)
  - Associazione Pedagogica Italiana - Siracusa (Bruno Ficili), 1989 (Folder 8: 9)
  - Astra, Gunnar, 1973-1983 (Folder 8: 10)
  - Aucouturier, Michel, 1974-1975 (Folder 8: 11)
  - Autre Europe (Wladimir Berelowitch), 1985 (Folder 8: 12)
  - Bakstrem, Annika, 1975-1976 (Folder 8: 13)
  - Bamdas, T., 1995. (Folder 8: 14)
    Includes photocopy of Golub' by M. Bamdas
  - Barat, Leonid, 1975 (Folder 8: 15)
  - Bard College, 1990 (Folder 8: 16)
  - Belgische Radio en Televisie, 1990 (Folder 8: 17)
  - Belinkova, Natalia, 1974-1976 (Folder 8: 18)
  - Belknap, Robert, n.d. (Folder 8: 19)
  - Bellow, Saul, 1984 (Folder 8: 20)
  - Berberova, Nina, 1971-1976 (Folder 8: 21)
  - Bethell, Nicholas, 1979-1993 (Folder 8: 22)
  - Bienek, Horst, 1980-1988 (Folder 8: 23)
  - Blake, Patricia, 1979 (Folder 8: 24)
  - Bogoraz, I., 1975 (Folder 8: 25)
  - Bolenko, Anatolii, 1987 (Folder 8: 26)
  - Böll, René, 1986 (Folder 8: 27)
  - Borev, Iulii, 1991 (Folder 8: 28)
  - Bregel', Iurii, 1980 (Folder 8: 29)
  - Brigham Young University, 1975 (Folder 8: 30)
  - British Broadcasting Corporation, 1980 (Folder 8: 31)
  - Brown, Edward, 1988 (Folder 8: 32)
  - Brumberg, Abraham, 1978 (Folder 8: 33)
  - Canadian Broadcasting Corporation, 1975 (Folder 8: 34)
  - Cardoze, Michel (L'Humanité), n.d. (Folder 8: 35)
  - Carlisle, Olga, 1985 (Folder 8: 36)
  - Carolina Quarterly, 1974 (Folder 8: 37)
  - Ceke, Katalin, 1995 (Folder 8: 38)
  - Cemovic, Momcilo, 1995 (Folder 8: 39)
  - Centre Georges Pompidou, Bibliothèque Publique d'Information, 1989 (Folder 8: 40)
  - Centro Studi e Ricerca sull'Identità Culturale Europea, 1989 (Folder 8: 41)
  - Chalidze, Valerii, 1974-1980 (Folder 8: 42)
  - Chatelaine, H., 1974 (Folder 8: 43)
  - Chinnov, Igor', 1974 (Folder 8: 44)
  - Columbia University, 1979-1995 (Folder 8: 45)
  - Comité Martchenko, 1987 (Folder 8: 46)
  - Cornell University (George Gibian), 1973 (Folder 8: 47)
  - Dalton, M., 1973 (Folder 8: 48)
  - Danilevskii, A., 1993 (Folder 8: 49)
  - Débat, n.d. (Folder 8: 50)
  - 52 Demokraticheskoe Ob"edinenie, 1981 (Folder 8: 51)
  - Dessaix, Robert, 1974 (Folder 8: 52)
  - Deutsche Welle, 1978-1986 (Folder 8: 53)
  - Dewhurst, Martin, 1975-1986 (Folder 8: 54)
  - Djordjevich, Mirko, 1990-1991 (Folder 8: 55)
  - Dol'nik, Solomon, 1974-1977 (Folder 8: 56)
  - Donatov, L., 1974 (Folder 8: 57)
  - Dovlatov, Sergei, 1980-1987. (Folder 8: 58)
    Includes copies of correspondence between Dovlatov and Vladimir Maramzin, and clippings re conference entitled "Russian Literature in Emigration: The Third Wave," Los Angeles, 1981
  - Draitser, Emil, 1985 (Folder 8: 59)
  - Druzhnikov, Iurii, 1993-1995 (Folder 8: 60)
  - École des Hautes Études en Sciences Sociales, Paris, (Jutta Scherrer), 1979 (Folder 8: 61)
  - Éditions Albin Michel, 1991 (Folder 8: 62)
  - Éditions du Seuil, 1980 (Folder 9: 1)
  - Éditions Gallimard, 1980 (Folder 9: 2)
  - Ehrlich, Victor, 1973-1976 (Folder 9: 3)
  - Encyclopaedia Universalis, n.d. (Folder 9: 4)
  - Esenin-Volpin, Aleksandr, 1990 (Folder 9: 5)
  - Etkind, Efim, 1980-1984 (Folder 9: 6)
  - Europa letteraria (Giancarlo Vigorelli), 1975 (Folder 9: 7)
  - Fanger, Donald, 1974-1984 (Folder 9: 8)
  - Farrar, Straus & Giroux, Inc., 1976 (Folder 9: 9)
  - Des femmes, 1987 (Folder 9: 10)
  - Field, Andrew, 1973-1974 (Folder 9: 11)
  - Filip, Ota, 1982 (Folder 9: 12)
  - Filippov, Boris, 1974 (Folder 9: 13)
  - Fleishman, Lazar, 1974-1991 (Folder 9: 14)
  - Fondation pour la Liberté et les Droits de l'Homme, 1975 (Folder 9: 15)
  - Fondazione Ambrosiana Paolo VI, 1987. (Folder 9: 16)
    Includes program for conference
  - Fosty, Vera, 1974-1975. (Folder 9: 17)
    Includes clipping of her article re V teni Gogolia
  - Frank, Joseph, 1991 (Folder 9: 18)
  - Friedberg, Maurice, 1979-1986 (Folder 9: 19)
  - Fundación Pablo Iglesias, 1991-1992 (Folder 9: 20)
  - Geier, Svetlana, 1974 (Folder 9: 21)
  - Genis, Aleksandr, 1985-1998 (Folder 9: 22)
  - Ginodman, Inna, 1984-1987 (Folder 9: 23)
  - Giornale nuovo, 1979 (Folder 9: 24)
  - Glenny, Michael, 1975-1985 (Folder 9: 25)
  - Golos Sarubeschia (Vera Pirozhkova), 1973-1980 (Folder 9: 26)
  - Gorbacheva, A., 1991 (Folder 9: 27)
  - Gorbanevskii, Mikhail, 1990 (Folder 9: 28)
  - Gulliver Amsterdam, 1989-1990 (Folder 9: 29)
  - Günther-Hielscher, Karla, 1990 (Folder 9: 30)
  - Gurevich, Aleksandr, 1989-1994 (Folder 9: 31)
  - Gut, Taja, 1984 (Folder 9: 32)
  - Hamon, Leo, 1974 (Folder 9: 33)
  - Hayward, Max, 1976-1977 (Folder 9: 34)
  - Hegge, Per, 1976 (Folder 9: 35)
  - Helsingen Sanomat, 1989 (Folder 9: 36)
  - Hofstra University, 1978 (Folder 9: 37)
  - Hokkaido University, n.d. (Folder 9: 38)
  - Howe, Irving, 1979 (Folder 9: 39)
  - Hudson Review, 1978 (Folder 9: 40)
  - Index on Censorship, 1990 (Folder 9: 41)
  - Institut Baden Literackich, 1993-1995 (Folder 9: 42)
  - Institut Universitaire d'Études Européennes, 1989 (Folder 9: 43)
  - Institute of Modern Russian Culture, 1979-1984 (Folder 9: 44)
  - International Sakharov Committee and International Sakharov Hearings, 1975-1986 (Folder 9: 45)
  - Iofe, V. and L., 1991-1993 (Folder 9: 46)
  - Ivask, Iurii, 1973-1975., See also SINTAKSIS FILE/Manuscripts submitted for publication (Folder 9: 47)
  - Izdatel'stvo "Sovetskii Pisatel'," 1993 (Folder 9: 48)
  - Jokubinas, Kestutis, 1976-1994 (Folder 9: 49)
  - Joufré, B., 1980 (Folder 9: 50)
  - Kaspar Hauser, 1985 (Folder 9: 51)
  - Kataoka, Miiko, 1980-1982 (Folder 9: 52)
  - Kazack, Wolfgang, 1973-1990 (Folder 9: 53)
  - Khalif, Lev, 1979 (Folder 9: 54)
  - Kirk, Irina, 1973- (Folder 9: 55)
  - Kitaevich, Iulii, 1985-1992 (Folder 9: 56)
  - Kolonosky, Walter, 1993-1994 (Folder 9: 57)
  - Konstantinovskii, Il'ia, n.d. (Folder 9: 58)
  - Kontinent, 1975-1996 (Folder 9: 59)
  - Kopylev, Lev, 1991 (Folder 9: 60)
  - Kossman, Nina, 1991 (Folder 9: 61)
  - Ktorova, Alla, 1980-1987 (Folder 9: 62)
  - Kulmaganbetov, Makhmet, n.d. (Folder 9: 63)
  - Lawrence, John, Sir, 1974 (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - Leong, Albert, 1996 (Folder 10: 2)
  - Levin, Ilya (Folder 10: 3)
  - Limanovskii, Anatolii, 1990-1994 (Folder 10: 4)
  - Literaturnaia Gazeta, n.d. (Folder 10: 5)
  - Literaturnoe obozrenie, 1992 (Folder 10: 6)
  - Litvinov, Pavel, 1986 (Folder 10: 7)
  - Lourie, Richard, 1975-1986 (Folder 10: 8)
  - Lur'i, Iurii, 1974 (Folder 10: 9)
  - Magisterium, 1993 (Folder 10: 10)
  - Malmstad, John, 1984 (Folder 10: 11)
  - Maltsev, Iurii, 1970-1975 (Folder 10: 12)
  - Mandel'shtam, Nadezhda, 1974 (Folder 10: 13)
  - Marcadé, Jean-Claude, 1974 (Folder 10: 14)
  - Markizh, Sima, n.d. (Folder 10: 15)
  - Martinez, Louis, 1975-1980 (Folder 10: 16)
  - Massachusetts Review, 1990 (Folder 10: 17)
  - Matich, Olga, 1983-1984 (Folder 10: 18)
  - Men'shutina, Lidiia, n.d. (Folder 10: 19)
  - Mezhdunarodnyi fond slavianskoi pis'mennosti i kul'tury, 1992 (Folder 10: 20)
  - Mikhailov, Misha, 1974-1988 (Folder 10: 21)
  - Misjon bak Jernteppet, 1973 (Folder 10: 22)
  - Moberg, Thomas, 1996 (Folder 10: 23)
  - Mochizuki, Tetsuo, 1992 (Folder 10: 24)
  - Mozhaev, Lev, 1986-1987 (Folder 10: 25)
  - National Endowment for Democracy, 1987 (Folder 10: 26)
  - Natsional'nyi trudovoi soiuz, 1982-1984. (Folder 10: 27)
    Includes material re N.T.S. and correspondence of Uirii Chikarleev
  - Nekrich, Aleksandr, 1974 (Folder 10: 28)
  - Nemchinov, Sergei, 1975 (Folder 10: 29)
  - Nepomnyashchy, Catherine, 1986 (Folder 10: 30)
  - New Republic (Leon Wieseltier), 1990 (Folder 10: 31)
  - New York Center for Visual History, 1990 (Folder 10: 32)
  - Nezavisimaia Gazeta, 1991 (Folder 10: 33)
  - Ninov, A., 1991 (Folder 10: 34)
  - Niqueux, Michel, 1974 (Folder 10: 35)
  - Nivat, Georges, 1973-1989 (Folder 10: 36)
  - Norwich University, Russian School (Konstantin Kustanovich), 1996 (Folder 10: 37)
  - Nouvel observateur, 1964-1978 (Folder 10: 38)
  - Novoye Russkoye Slovo (Andrei Sedykh), 1975-1980 (Folder 10: 39)
  - Novyi Amerikanets, 1980 (Folder 10: 40)
  - Novyi mir, 1963 (Folder 10: 41)
  - Numano, Mitsuyoshi, 1985-1996 (Folder 10: 42)
  - Obolenskii, Dimitrii, 1974 (Folder 10: 43)
  - Overli, Jorn Simen, 1993 (Folder 10: 44)
  - Overseas Publications Interchange Limited, 1979 (Folder 10: 45)
  - Oxford University Press, Central and East European Publishing Project (Sally Laird), 1991 (Folder 10: 46)
  - Papernyi, Zinovii, 1991 (Folder 10: 47)
  - Partisan Review, 1982-1990 (Folder 10: 48)
  - Pasternak, Evgenii, 1980 (Folder 10: 49)
  - Pasternak, Josephine, 1983., See also PHOTOGRAPHS (Folder 10: 50)
  - Patrushev, Vasilii, 1989-1990 (Folder 10: 51)
  - Perlmuter, Vadim, 1995 (Folder 10: 52)
  - Petersen, Franz (Nikolai Polianskii), 1989 (Folder 10: 53)
  - Petovradzhi, Mikhail, 1978 (Folder 10: 54)
  - Petrov, Nikolai, 1986-1987., See also SINTAKSIS FILE/Manuscripts submitted for publication (Folder 10: 55)
  - Pirozhkova, A., 1989 (Folder 10: 56)
  - Pirozhkova, Vera, 1974 (Folder 10: 57)
  - Popovskii, Mark, 1979-1987 (Folder 10: 58)
  - Porudomiskii, Vladimir, 1991 (Folder 10: 59)
  - Possev-Verlag (Lev Rahr), 1974 (Folder 10: 60)
  - Rabinovich, Stanley, 1985-1998 (Folder 10: 61)